בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So we start today a new מסכת, Masechet,
עירובין, Eruvin, which is long, not as long as שבת, Shabbos, but
it'll last us about three months. And its primary focus is on
two types of עירוב. Eiruv. We normally call עירוב, Eiruv, I should
mention, what in the תורה Torah is really צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach,
which is we call the עירוב Eiruv the beams and the wires
which define everything as sort of become substitute walls and define the
outdoor space as a private domain or רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. That's
not what is actually called עירוב. Eiruv. עירוב Eiruv is actually
when you have multiple houses opening up into one courtyard, they all
have to join together, ערב, arev, it's like to
commingle in a loaf of bread so that it's defined as sort
of one property and not multiple properties. So that's basically what עירוב
Eiruv is.
There's עירובי חצירות eiruvei chatzeiros and שיתופי מבואות, shitufei mevoos, which is
שיתופי מבואות shitufei mevoos is when multiple courtyards open up into one
alley. But anyway, that's one aspect of עירובין. Eruvin. עירובין Eruvin is
in the plural because another thing that an עירוב Eiruv is is
that it allows you to walk more outside of a city. You're
given two thousand אמות amos in every direction, but if you want
to go more than two thousand אמות amos in one direction, you
can designate your place you began שבת Shabbos as a certain point
outside of the city and that'll give you more distance in that
direction but it'll take it away from the other direction. And you
also do that with a loaf of bread or with some food.
So again, food sort of refining very fundamentally here where you live,
where you're present. And as I mentioned yesterday when we finished שבת,
Shabbos, it's interesting, the beginning of מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos also opens
up with a focus on bread and food, the giving to the
poor person. Anyway, those are technically what's called the עירוב, Eiruv, the
joining together of the courtyards or of the houses or of the
setting of a place outside of the city, which is where you
are considered to begin שבת. Shabbos. Our משנה Mishnah begins with the
types of considerations that are more what we discuss when we talk
about עירוב, Eiruv, which is defining the walls. How do you make
walls when there are not really, when there aren't really walls? How
do you create walls? And let's take a look. So the משנה
Mishnah begins as following: מבוי. Mavoi. A מבוי mavoi is an alleyway.
Now,
as I said, basically the configuration is that you have multiple houses
that open up into a חצר. chatzer. Think about like a court.
You have multiple houses that open up into a חצר. chatzer. If
the court is all, the yard is all surrounded by houses and
the walls of the houses, if they're tightly packed, effectively become walls
around that court.
So that is a חצר. chatzer. Then if you have multiple courts
opening up into another yard or
into a thoroughfare, that is a מבוי. mavoi. Okay, so you can
have,
so you have your houses here opening up into a
חצר, chatzer, these are houses. And then you have your multiple
חצרות, chatzeros, each one of these is the same thing, your multiple
חצרות chatzeros opening up into an alleyway, which is a מבוי. mavoi.
Now if a מבוי mavoi only has things on the two sides
and not on that end, it would be considered a מבוי מפולש,
mavoi mefulash, an open-ended מבוי, mavoi, and that could actually be like
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, because there it would be basically a
street. But if it dead-ends to a חצר, chatzer, then it's A,
it's not רשות הרבים reshus harabim because it's just not a straight
thoroughfare, and B, it might even be רשות היחיד reshus hayachid if
all these walls effectively are walls of the מבוי, mavoi, then it's
actually surrounded by three walls. If the, assuming again all the houses
are packed tightly enough. Okay, so that's what you have as your
מבוי. mavoi. So you have a מבוי mavoi here.
So question: does the definition of a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
does it not include at all ownership? Biblically it does not, good
question. Right, although we define רשות היחיד reshus hayachid as private domain,
biblically it's not about ownership. Rabbinically, that's what the עירובי חצירות eiruvei
chatzeiros and שיתופי מבואות shitufei mevoos does, is that it makes it
as if there's only one owner to the entire space, but that's
only needed at a rabbinical level. Biblically, as long as it has
three walls or four walls or whatever it is, that's רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid regardless of if it has multiple ownership. Okay.
And does individual ownership, is that a factor in making something a
רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid?
No, meaning like, so you have like, if you have like a
public domain that was open by a, owned by a particular certain
person, ownership has nothing to do with the definition of רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid or רשות הרבים reshus harabim at a biblical level. רשות
הרבים Reshus harabim is all functionally it's served to be either a
like large gathering place or it's a major thoroughfare, and רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid is a space surrounded by three walls. It's a very
good point. Ownership has nothing to do with it, it's all about
its function. But this, if it's surrounded by three walls, could be
a biblical רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, but the whole idea of עירוב
eiruv is to combine it all as into one ownership. For rabbinically
for it to count as such.
Well, why is that necessary, I guess?
Because the rabbis felt that the reality that multiple different owners are
using the same space made it experientially less of a רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid. So we'll see about that. Okay, so our משנה mishna
begins with the מבוי. mavoy. Now, if you have this מבוי mavoy
that is surrounded by houses and courtyards on three sides, then what
you need to do for the fourth side, you need some type
of a symbol
or some type of a marker, I should say, on the fourth
side. You don't need—thank you—you don't need a fourth wall, but you
do need something to serve to make it good, because three walls
alone is not enough. So what you need is either a לחי
lechi or a קורה. kora. Right, a לחי lechi is a vertical
beam and a קורה kora is a horizontal beam. So on that
fourth side—thank you—on that fourth side of the courtyard, you need one
of those in order to allow you to carry in the courtyard.
That's besides the idea of joining together in the bread, but first
we're focusing on structurally what you need on that fourth side.
You say like a crossbeam or a vertical beam?
Yes, or vertical beam, one or the other. Okay, so מבוי שגבוה
למעלה מעשרים אמה. mavoy she-gavoa lemala me-esrim ama. Now we start by
talking about the crossbeam. If the crossbeam is higher than twenty אמות
amot off the floor, ימעט, yima-et, you have to lower it. It's
not good the way it is. רבי יהודה אומר אין צריך, Rabbi
Yehuda omer ein tzarich, you don't need to. והרחב מעשר אמות, ve-harachav
me-eser amot, now let's say the opening of the street is greater
than ten אמות amot wide, the street is more than ten אמות
amot wide. So again, if you want to consider this fourth side
as if it's a fourth wall—you know, the way you're going to
do it conceptually what we look at it is like you have
three walls here and then so you don't have anything on the
fourth wall, but that's an opening. So you know it's a door,
it's a doorway. That's okay. Okay, so you maybe have this or
this which are components of a doorway, like, you know, the lintel
or the doorpost. So it basically effectively is like a doorway. That's
fine and that's all you need. But if that opening, that fourth
side, is more than—excuse me—more than עשר אמות, eser amot, you know
ten אמות, amot, and an אמה ama is about a foot and
a half, more than fifteen feet, after a certain point you can't
consider it a doorway. That's just like a, you know, a break
in the wall. So that's a problem if it's more than עשר
אמות. eser amot.
So if it's a gate, you know?
Okay, well, we'll see in the גמרא. gemara. Okay, והרחב מעשר אמות
ימעט. ve-harachav me-eser amot yima-et. So then you have to make it
a smaller gap, you know, maybe by making like partial walls at
the edges. But the fourth side cannot be bigger than עשר אמות
eser amot wide. ואם יש לו צורת הפתח אף על פי שהוא
רחב מעשר אמות אין צריך למעט. ve-im yesh lo tzurat hapetach af
al pi she-hu rachav me-eser amot ein tzarich lema-et. But if you
have a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, now a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
is all the components of a doorway. It's not either the vertical
or the horizontal; it's both two vertical beams and the horizontal beam.
That's a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. So if you have that going
here, even if it's wider than עשר אמות, eser amot, the very
fact that you have the entire structure of a doorframe, which a
צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach means a doorframe—right, that defines it as a
fourth wall as an opening. Okay, and you might already begin to
think that that's where, you know, how we make our עירובים eruvs
in contemporary practice is by putting, you know, posts, we put like
these two-by-fours against
the telephone poles, and directly under the wire that's the electric wire.
So therefore, or the telephone wire, whatever it is. Anyway, so then
you have that at another pole. So those are the two beams
and they don't have to actually touch the wire, they just have
to be directly under it. And then the wire which runs directly
over, that's the horizontal beam. So that creates the צורת הפתח. tzurat
hapetach. Okay, but here you actually have three real walls and you're
just using the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach for the fourth.
It's funny because צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach doesn't really look like a
doorframe, so no one's going to say that you're—well,
we'll talk about right, what are the exact—what are the exact הלכתיים
halachic requirements of צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Yeah, we'll see that. So
let's look at the גמרא. gemara.
Sorry, just a little sick. תנן התם, tnan hatam, we taught over
there in סוכה. Sukka. The גמרא gemara סוכה Sukka opens with a
very similar משנה. mishna. סוכה שגבוהה למעלה מעשרים אמה פסולה. Sukka she-gavoha
lemala me-esrim ama pesula. A סוכה sukka higher than twenty אמות amos
is invalid. ורבי יהודה מכשיר, ve-rabbi Yehuda machshir, Rabbi Yehuda says it's
kosher. Seems like very parallel. The גמרא gemara says מאי שנא גבי
סוכה דתני פסולה וגבי מבוי דתני תקנתא? mai shna gabi sukka de-tani
pesula ve-gabi mavoy de-tani takanta? Why by סוכה sukka does it say
פסולה, pesula, invalid, and here it says תקנתא, takanta, fix it? Why
didn't he here—you know, he could have said the same by סוכה,
sukka, fix it. So why doesn't it say either פסול pasul in
both places or ימעט yima-et in both places? Why does it say
something slightly different?
So let's see what the גמרא gemara says. סוכה דאורייתא תני פסולה
מבוי דרבנן תני תקנתא. sukka de-oraisa tani pesula mavoy de-rabanan tani takanta.
So סוכה sukka is biblical, it says פסול, pasul, מבוי mavoy is
rabbinic, it says how to fix it. What does that mean? So
רש״י Rashi says what it means is that
סוכה—like sukka the fact whether a סוכה sukka was kosher or not
existed before the משנה mishna was written.
There's a reality, the תורה Torah tells you build a סוכה. sukka.
So the משנה mishna is like informing you that if you did
this, your סוכה sukka is פסול. pasul. Whereas by the מבוי... mavoy...
It can't say פסול pasul somehow until it's already at first has
told you that you have to make a מבוי. mavoi. So it's
not like it's a pre-existing institution to tell you I mean not
a מבוי mavoi the crossbeam, you know, so that it could use
that label of פסול pasul before first informing you what the requirements
are. Which is a little bit strange because of course then the
question is, well why not actually that's a good point, why not
start this מסכת masechet by telling me what the requirements are rather
than telling me by what makes it invalid? What? The same question?
Yeah, exactly. So, you know, תוספות Tosafot actually says, if you look
at the very first תוספות, Tosafot, מבוי שהיה גבוה מעשרים אמה ימעיט,
Mavoi she-hayah gavoha me-esrim ama yima'et, תוספות Tosafot
says: הקשו בארעא דמערבא Hikshu b'ar'a d'ma'arava דהוי ליה לאשמעינן הכשר מבוי
ברישא. de-havi lei le-ashmi'inan hachshar mavoi b'reisha. First tell me what makes
a מבוי mavoi כשר. kasher. בלחי וקורה Bi-lechi ve-korah either a vertical
or a horizontal beam and then say ואם הניח למעלה מעשרים אמה
ימעיט ve-im hinni'ach le-ma'la me-esrim ama yima'et and then say if you
do it lower, higher than twenty אמות amos you have to lower
the horizontal beam. So says okay the reason maybe it started this
way was because it starts the same way in מסכת סוכה masechet
Sukkah so to make it parallel. Which could also raise questions of
why it starts the same way in מסכת סוכה. masechet Sukkah. So
right so that so the basic point is is that in general
for whatever reason and maybe this had something to do with the
nature of an oral culture and how things were organized you know
like let's just say nobody asked רמב"ם, Rambam, רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi never did ask רמב"ם Rambam before deciding how to organize
the משנה. Mishna. So there it always seems to start like not
from the most like first principles and then go forward but often
very often starts from some secondary point. Anyway that's the first answer
of the גמרא Gemara which רש"י Rashi says is the point since
we didn't yet tell you about that מבוי mavoi we couldn't say
פסולה. pesula. תוספות Tosafot has a different answer but let's see now
what the גמרא Gemara says. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואיבעית אימא Ve-iba'it eima if you
want you could say דאורייתא נמי תני תקנתא. d'oraita nami tani takanta.
Even by biblical things we would tell you how to fix it.
So and we wouldn't necessarily have to say פסולה. pesula. אלא סוכה
Ela Sukkah so why didn't we say that by סוכה? Sukkah? דנפישי
מילי Di-nefishei milei
there would have taken a lot of words. פסק ותני פסולה Pasak
ve-tani pesula it just simply says פסולה. pesula. מבוי דלא נפישי מילי
Mavoi d'lo nafishei milei מבוי mavoi didn't take a lot of words
תני תקנתא tani takanta it says תקנתא. takanta. What does that mean?
Because the first משנה mishna in סוכה Sukkah tells you three ways
סוכה Sukkah could be פסול. pasul. It's higher than twenty אמות, amos,
actually four maybe, it has more sun than shade, it has less
than three walls, or it's lower than ten טפחים. tefachim. And says
in all those cases פסולה. pesula. So if it was going to
tell you how to fix it it'd have to tell you four
different ways to fix it. If it's higher than twenty אמות amos
lower it, if it's lower than ten טפחים tefachim raise it, if
it has less than three walls add another you know whatever. So
that would have been very verbose. So therefore says in any of
those cases פסול. pasul. Here it's only giving you one scenario so
it can tell you lower it. Okay so that was just a
slight sort of tangential linguistic point.
There is a general verb for fixing things.
What? לתקן? Le-taken? Okay I guess then why do you need to
say it then it'd be obvious I guess. Anyway
okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav. Now
we get to the sort of more substance of what we're talking
about. חכמים לא למדו אלא מפתחו של היכל. Chachamim lo lamdu ela
mi-pitcho shel Heichal. The גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that what
the idea of this fourth open end of the מבוי mavoi has
to be in order to allow you to carry in the מבוי
mavoi it has to be considered like I told you a doorway,
an opening, not just like if there's no wall there it has
to be considered like like a doorway. So and that's going to
teach and so where are we going to learn what parameters are
acceptable? Why does it have to be how do you know twenty
אמות amos high, ten אמות amos wide, how do you know those
are the limits for what defines something? Actually so you take look
alright we'll take a look. So so where are we going to
get this as an idea what are the parameters for a doorway?
So max the maximum parameters. ורבי יהודה לא למדו אלא מפתחו של
אולם. Ve-Rabbi Yehuda lo lamdu ela mi-pitcho shel ulam.
So the rabbis learned it from the doorway to the היכל Heichal
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda from the doorway to the אולם. Ulam.
The היכל Heichal is what parallels in the תורה Torah the משכן.
Mishkan. It's the opening you go into and then you have the
מנורה menorah and the שולחן shulchan and the golden and the מזבח
הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. The אולם Ulam did not exist in the משכן.
Mishkan. It existed in the time of שלמה Shlomo in the second
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and it was a like it was a
hall prior to going into the היכל Heichal and it extended beyond
the width of the היכל Heichal like if this was the היכל
Heichal
then the אולם Ulam sort of looked like this and it was
added at the time of שלמה. Shlomo. So the doorway here right
was a certain height and this was even a much bigger doorway.
Okay anyway I know I went from two dimensions to three dimensions
but you'll figure but you get the idea. Okay anyway so that's
the אולם Ulam and the היכל. Heichal. So the rabbis learned it
from the opening of the היכל Heichal and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
learned it from the opening of the אולם. Ulam. What constitutes an
opening? דתנן Ditnan
it's taught in the משנה. mishna.
פתחו של היכל גבוה עשרים אמה. Pitcho shel Heichal gavoha esrim ama.
The height of the היכל Heichal is עשרים אמה esrim ama high
ורחבו עשר אמות ve-rachbo eser amot and it's עשר אמות eser amot
wide. So you understand why רב Rav said that that's the basis
for the חכמים Chachamim it's exactly the maximum parameters in our משנה
mishna עשרים אמה esrim ama high by עשר אמות eser amot wide.
ושל אולם גבוה ארבעים אמה ורחבו עשרים אמה Ve-shel ulam gavoha arba'im
ama v'rachbo esrim ama and the אולם Ulam is ארבעים אמה arba'im
ama tall high and עשרים אמה esrim ama wide. So while in
our
משנה... mishna... Double. Double, yeah. ושתיהם לא למדוה אלא Ushteihem lo lemaduha
ella where am I משמעי דקרא דרשי. Mishmei dekra darshi. They both
learned from one פסוק. pasuk. ושחט פתח אהל מועד, Veshachat petach ohel
moed, you should slaughter... ושחטו פתח אהל מועד, Veshachatu petach ohel moed,
you should slaughter by the opening of the אהל מועד. ohel moed.
דרבנן, Derabbanan, I'm sorry,
let me just sound... Okay. דרבנן Derabbanan סברי savri קדושת היכל לחוד
וקדושת אולם לחוד, kedushat Heichal lachud vekedushat Ulam lachud, that the sanctity
of the אולם Ulam is distinct from the sanctity of the היכל.
Heichal. You could not, if you're in the אולם, Ulam, you are
not considered that you're in the היכל. Heichal. So if you have
to slaughter something, so the key here being that it refers to
the opening of the אהל מועד, ohel moed, it uses the phrase
פתח. petach. So is the, the question is, is the אולם Ulam
considered part of the אהל מועד ohel moed so that the label
פתח petach would refer to the door of the אולם? Ulam? So
the rabbis say the sanctity of the היכל Heichal is distinct from
the sanctity of the אולם Ulam and only the היכל Heichal is
considered to be the אהל מועד. ohel moed. וכי כתיב פתח אהל
מועד, Vechi ketiv petach ohel moed, so the phrase פתח אהל מועד,
petach ohel moed, אהיכל כתיב, a-Heichal ketiv, only refers to the היכל,
Heichal, only the היכל Heichal is considered to be the sanctity of
אהל מועד ohel moed and therefore only the opening of the היכל
Heichal is labeled a פתח. petach. רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi Yehuda savar,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds היכל ואולם קדושה אחת היא. Heichal ve-Ulam
kedusha achat hi. No,
the היכל Heichal is part, the אולם Ulam is part of the
sanctity of the היכל. Heichal. So the opening of the אולם Ulam
is also considered the opening of the אהל מועד. ohel moed. That's
transferring the reality in the מדבר midbar to what you have after
you have a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. וכי כתיב פתח אהל מועד,
Vechi ketiv petach ohel moed, so when it says the opening of
אהל מועד ohel moed in the משכן, mishkan, אהתרוייהו כתיב, a-travaihu ketiv,
it would refer when you had a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash either
to the opening of the היכל Heichal or the opening of the
אולם. Ulam. So since the אולם Ulam is part of the היכל
Heichal according to him, the door of the אולם Ulam is also
considered a פתח petach and therefore you go by its parameters which
are 40 high and 20 wide and not the smaller parameters of
the היכל. Heichal. Okay, so that's the one explanation.
Yeah, that's a big difference between prescriptive and descriptive, right? The תורה
Torah as far as I recall doesn't specify the dimensions of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's just what שלמה Shlomo decides to build.
Well, although the גמרא Gemara does say, quotes the פסוק pasuk where
it says הכל בכתב מיד
ה' עלי השכיל,
Hakol bichtav miyad
Hashem alai hiskil, הכל בכתב מיד ה' עלי השכיל, Hakol bichtav miyad
Hashem alai hiskil, I mean according to the גמרא Gemara the dimensions
of בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash were revealed in רוח הקודש ruach hakodesh
and so on, right. So yeah, the גמרא Gemara so yeah.
Yeah, but I mean still, if you're a strict constructionist view, so
to speak,
and שבת Shabbat the whole big deal was the משכן, mishkan, you'd
really think משכן, mishkan, משכן, mishkan, משכן mishkan and you know, so
then I still find it kind of interesting the drawing in a
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. I understand it's...
Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to get to it. Let's wait.
The גמרא Gemara will identify tell you how you can identify משכן
mishkan and בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But right now we're saying that
the whole key is the word פתח petach and what does that
פתח petach in the משכן mishkan correspond in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, only the היכל Heichal or even the אולם? Ulam?
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, איבעית אימא, Ibayis eima, if you want I could say לרבי
יהודה נמי קדושת אולם לחוד קדושת היכל לחוד, le-Rabbi Yehuda nami kedushat
ulam lachud kedushat Heichal lachud, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not going
to claim that the אולם Ulam is part of the היכל. Heichal.
That's distinct. Nevertheless, והכא היינו טעמא דרבי יהודה, ve-hacha hainu taama de-Rabbi
Yehuda,
here's the reason רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda considers the opening of the
אולם Ulam also to be the parameters of a פתח, petach, דכתיב
אל פתח אולם הבית, de-chetiv el petach ulam habayis,
because as the verse says by the opening of the אולם Ulam
of the hall of the house. So you see the phrase פתח
petach refers to the אולם Ulam as well. Now if anybody of
you have your גמרות, Gemaras, you will say you will be looking
at the side to say where is this פסוק? pasuk? And there
is no cross-reference. Look at תוספות, Tosafot, דכתיב אל פתח אולם הבית,
de-chetiv el petach ulam habayis, זה פסוק אינו בשום
מקום.
zeh pasuk
eino beshum makom. So he basically quotes the רי Ri that says
it's a hybrid of two separate פסוקים, pesukim, okay, and then figures
out how to make sense of that in the גמרא Gemara since
it doesn't really exist as a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so it's quite
fascinating. Alright, back to the גמרא, Gemara, recognizing that the פסוק pasuk
doesn't exactly exist. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, and the rabbis would say back, אי
הוה כתיב אל פתח אולם, ei hava ketiv el petach ulam, if
it had just said פתח אולם, petach ulam, כדקאמרת, kedakamart, then you'd
be... good point, that the opening of the אולם Ulam is called
a פתח. petach. השתא דכתיב אל פתח אולם הבית, hashta dachetiv el
petach ulam habayis, now it says the opening of the אולם Ulam
of the hall of the house, הבית הפתוח לאולם, habayis hapatuach le-ulam,
it doesn't mean the opening, the doorway, it means
the house that opens into the hall or the hall that opens
into the house, but the word פתח petach here does not refer
to actually the doorway itself. Okay, which again, very strange that they're
subdividing that פסוק pasuk if it doesn't even exist, if it's not
even a פסוק. pasuk. But okay.
So wait, I'm sorry, what would be the house that opens into
the אולם? Ulam? Or the other way around, the היכל Heichal opens
into the אולם Ulam you're saying? Yeah, what was in front.
So what would be the house that opens into the אולם? Ulam?
No, I assume it means, I assume it meant say
the עזרה, azarah, not the היכל. Heichal. I don't know, maybe it
means the היכל. Heichal. Yeah, well the... I don't know, maybe you're
right, maybe it's the היכל. Heichal. Alright, anyway, גמרא Gemara continues, הכי
כתיב האי. hachi ketiv hai. Now the question back to what everybody
else was asking, האי במשכן כתיב. hai be-mishkan ketiv. One minute, this
פסוק pasuk about פתח petach is written by the אהל מועד, ohel
moed, it's written by the משכן. mishkan. How do you
apply... No, the משכן Mishkan is sometimes called the מקדש Mikdash and
the מקדש Mikdash is called the משכן, Mishkan, so you can apply
one to the other. אלא אי אמרת הכי, Ella ei amrat hachi,
if you don't say that, הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, ha
d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, שלמים ששחטן קודם פתיחת דלתות ההיכל פסולים.
shlamim sheshachtan kodem pesichas dalsos haheichal pesulim. If you slaughter a שלמים
shlamim before you opened up the doors of the היכל Heichal in
the morning, they're invalid, שנאמר שחטו פתח אהל מועד. shene'emar shachato pesach
ohel moed. That's the פסוק pasuk we started with, slaughter it, the
שלמים, shlamim, by the opening of the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So
from there we learned that the doors have to be open, and
if you slaughter the שלמים shlamim before the doors were opened, it's
not good.
בזמן שפתוחין ולא בזמן שנעולין. Bizman shepesuchin velo bizman sheneulin. פתח Pesach
means also פתוח, pasuach, that it has to not just be where,
but the door has to be open and not closed. Okay, so
that's what you learn from that פסוק. pasuk. So how can you
learn that to apply it in, you know, after the time of
the משכן? Mishkan? והא כי כתיב האי במשכן כתיב. Ve'ha ki kesiv
hai be'Mishkan kesiv. That idea that it has to be the פתח
אהל מועד pesach ohel moed is written by the אהל מועד. Ohel
Moed. How can you apply that to the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
I mean, you could almost ask it by anything, right, anything we
learn by קרבנות. korbanos. How do you keep applying things that are
written by the משכן Mishkan into the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Clearly
we have to have a basis to say that, you know, what
corresponds to it in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you apply the
same הלכות halachos to its corresponding features in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash.
One minute. אלא, Ella, so therefore you see that you have to
learn one to the other. Now I should say by the way,
because that פתח אהל מועד, pesach ohel moed, so you can't slaughter
the קרבנות korbanos before you've opened the doors of the היכל, Heichal,
which corresponds to the אהל מועד Ohel Moed in the משכן. Mishkan.
תוספות Tosafos says, I don't get it, you can't שחט shacht any
קרבן korban before you've brought the תמיד של שחר. tamid shel shachar.
So what would be, right, you have to the תמיד tamid is
the first thing you bring in the morning, has to be the
first thing that's brought. So why do you need this special הלכה
halacha that the doors have to be open? Because, you know, you'd
have to bring the תמיד tamid anyway. And we know that you
have to שחט shacht the תמיד tamid with the doors of the
היכל Heichal open. So תוספות Tosafos says
if you שחט shecht something before the תמיד, tamid, maybe it wouldn't
be פסול. posul. From here we're learning that it's פסול. posul. Or
תוספות Tosafos says, let's say the doors got closed in the middle
of the day. That was an interesting... so anyway, for whatever reason
it is, in addition to the rule that the תמיד tamid have
to be the first thing, we also learn that if you bring
a קרבן korban when the doors of the היכל Heichal are closed,
that it's not valid. And that we learn for the היכל Heichal
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash from the אהל מועד Ohel Moed
of the
משכן. Mishkan. So. אלא אשכחן מקדש דאיקרי משכן ומשכן דאיקרי מקדש.
Ella ashkan Mikdash
de'ikri Mishkan ve'Mishkan de'ikri Mikdash. It has to be we learn one
from the other. So we, so the מקדש Mikdash is called the
משכן Mishkan and the משכן Mishkan is called the מקדש. Mikdash. Now,
it has to be because we apply, we know we apply all
the הלכות halachos of the משכן Mishkan to the מקדש. Mikdash. Now,
where do we actually learn this? בשלמא מקדש דאיקרי משכן דכתיב. Beshlama
Mikdash de'ikri Mishkan dikesiv. We understand the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is
also called a משכן Mishkan because it says ונתתי משכני בתוככם. Venasati
Mishkani besochechem. Right, that's at the end of ויקרא Vayikra in בחקתי
Bechukosai about, you know, the ברכות brachos and the קללות. klalos. And
it says I will give my משכן Mishkan in your midst. That's
in the future if you're doing all the מצוות. mitzvos. So the
question is, okay, but what do you mean, the משכן Mishkan is
already in our midst, they'd already built the משכן. Mishkan. So therefore
it must be referring to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So you
see the future בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is called a משכן. Mishkan.
אלא משכן דאיקרי מקדש מנלן? Ella Mishkan de'ikri Mikdash minalan? Where do
you know that the משכן Mishkan was called the מקדש? Mikdash? That
you sort of, you know, can link it both ways. אילימא
מדכתיב ונסעו הקהתים נשאי המקדש, Ilima mikesiv venasu hakehasim nosei hamikdash, that
the קהתים Kehasim who carry the מקדש Mikdash should carry it and
should travel והקימו את המשכן עד באם vehekimo es hamishkan ad boam
and should erect the משכן Mishkan before, you know, while everybody else
is coming, before they come. So here, one minute, והא האי בארון
כתיב, ve'ha hai be'Aron kesiv, that the מקדש Mikdash there does not
refer to the משכן, Mishkan, it refers to the ארון Aron because
the קהתים Kehasim only carry the ארון. Aron. So they carry the
holy vessels, so the מקדש Mikdash means the sanctified vessels. Right, it
does not mean, it does not mean the entire משכן. Mishkan. אלא
מהכא. Ella me'hacha. So, how about this פסוק? pasuk? ועשו לי מקדש
ושכנתי בתוכם. Ve'asu li mikdash veshachanti besocham. Okay, that was pretty easy.
You see name of מקדש. Mikdash.
So the משכן Mishkan is called the מקדש Mikdash and the מקדש
Mikdash is called a משכן. Mishkan. So anything that is true about
the משכן Mishkan is true about the מקדש Mikdash and vice versa.
Not exactly clear why you need vice versa since all the פסוקים
psukim are written by the משכן. Mishkan. But okay, once you've had
it by the משכן, Mishkan, you could apply it to the מקדש.
Mikdash. Yes, Charlie.
So, where you're, where
you're deriving this from the dimensions of the משכן. Mishkan. Yeah, but
the משכן Mishkan was quite a, was quite a bit smaller than
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Right, that's what Michael was asking. He says, you know, still, how
do you know that the same phrase פתח pesach applies? But presumably
the argument is, is that if the תורה Torah requires that there
be a פתח אהל מועד, pesach ohel moed, and we just learned
a minute ago that there're הלכות halachos that it's invalid to שחט
shacht a קרבן korban when it's not פתח אהל מועד pesach ohel
moed and so on. So clearly then what you have in the
מקדש Mikdash satisfies the requirements of פתח. pesach. That's the assumption of
the גמרא, Gemara, or else how could you שחט קרבנות shacht korbanos
if it doesn't satisfy the requirements of פתח? pesach? So, that, you're
right, it's different dimensions, but presumably if we're saying that it satisfies
what the, what those requirements are, we're saying that it still is
given that name.
I'm going to say two things on that. You know, well, one
is it still doesn't mean that for the purposes of הלכות halachos
of שבת Shabbat and, you know, you still don't learn it from
the משכן Mishkan per se because that's where everything else was learned.
I understand it's still considered a valid...
It's not about הלכות halachos on שבת, Shabbat, this is all about...
First of all, this is all about... First of all, let's start.
This way. This is all rabbinic. It has three walls. It's not
a biblical רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. It's probably already anyway a biblical
רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid because it has three walls. The fourth wall
is all rabbinic. Number one, okay? And and that's the biggest issue.
And number two is is that it's not talking about the the
the idea that you learn from the משכן Mishkan is that you
learn the actual activities that went into the construction of the משכן.
Mishkan. Here, we're learning about just architecturally what's considered to be a
wall, what's considered an opening, so it's not the same issue of
only learning exactly from the משכן. Mishkan.
Actually, once I say that, there was there was something interesting that
there you know there was training of sort of a ברכה משכנית,
Beracha Mishkanis, or said, Divine presence. Doesn't have to mean
I
understand what you're saying
is very literal.
I understand that. That's true.
It's like the rest of the ברכה Beracha almost.
Right.
Like to say that you can't carry once they begin,
yes.
So that's what I mentioned in that first תוספות. Tosfos. Yes, this
whole thing is very, like I said, nobody consulted רמב"ם Rambam about
how to organize the משניות. Mishnayos. You know the it's part of
a of an oral tradition. We're assuming the question is also who
are they writing it for? Like, are they writing it for the
uninitiated or are these things being basically written for people that are
already part of the whole ongoing conversation, you know, and therefore it's
not there's very rare there's sometimes but it's not often that you
get a sense that the משנה Mishnah feels like let's assume somebody
knows nothing, let's first you know lay out the first principles and
build from there.
And in פסחים, Pesachim, you do it with asking אור לארבעה עשר,
Or Le'arba'ah Asar, how do they know? And they knew but they
were still looking.
Yeah, it's somewhat true. The organization of the משניות. Mishnayos. Anyhow, first
using making an opening. All right. Anyway, let's move on. But yeah,
it's true. The organization is not what we would have liked. But
I do
but by the way, to repeat the point that I just made
to Michael, which is important, this idea of the need for a
fourth wall is not biblical. First of all, this certainly isn't a
רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim once it has three walls. It's at at
most it's a כרמלית, Karmelis, right? Because it's not a major thoroughfare.
It doesn't go it's not open-ended both ends. It's not a רשות,
Reshus, so it's not a biblical רשות Reshus once it has three
walls and it might even be רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid with three
walls. So the need of the fourth wall is only a rabbinic
requirement. So that's important to be aware of in general. Okay, so
let's continue. The גמרא Gemara says like
this: בין רבנן בין רבי יהודה ליאלפו מפתח שער החצר. Bein Rabbanan
bein Rabbi Yehudah liyalfu mipetach shaar hachatzer. So according whether according to
the Rabbis or according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, why are we
learning either from the אולם Ulam or the היכל? Heichal? Let's learn
learning from the opening of the courtyard and we're going back to
the משכן Mishkan here. דכתיב, Dechisiv, אורך החצר מאה באמה, Orech hachatzer
meah ba'amah,
the length was a hundred אמות Amos long. This is the open-air
courtyard around the משכן. Mishkan. ורוחב חמישים בחמישים, Verochav chamishim bachamishim, and
it was fifty by fifty wide. What fifty by fifty means we'll
talk about in a minute. Basically means that there was an open
space fifty by fifty.
Here you have, anyway,
if here is your משכן Mishkan and here's your חצר, Chatzer, okay?
So the חצר Chatzer is fifty wide. So this is fifty by
fifty and then the משכן Mishkan is thirty and then there's twenty
back here. So the courtyard is a hundred by fifty. You sort
of see that? You sort of, you know. Yeah. Okay.
Fifty, thirty and twenty.
So right in this is fifty and this is fifty. Okay. So
the courtyard so the whole thing is called the courtyard around the
משכן. Mishkan. It's a hundred by fifty, but it says fifty by
fifty because that's the open space before you get to the משכן.
Mishkan. That's how the גמרא Gemara understands it. So okay. So אורך
החצר מאה באמה ורוחב חמישים בחמישים. Orech hachatzer meah ba'amah verochav chamishim
bachamishim. It's a hundred long and fifty by fifty wide or fifty
wide. וקומה חמש אמות Vekumah chamesh amos and five אמות Amos tall.
דכתיב, Dechisiv, those are the, you know, curtains that are hanging all
around the open-air courtyard. דכתיב, Dechisiv, וחמש עשרה אמה קלעים לכתף, Vechamesh
esreih amah klaim lakasef, fifteen אמות Amos on one shoulder. וכתיב ולכתף
השנית מזה ומזה לשער החצר קלעים חמש עשרה אמה.
Uchisiv ulakasef hashenis mizeh umizeh leshaar
hachatzer klaim chamesh esreih amah. And fifteen אמות Amos on the other
shoulder. So here you have fifteen אמות Amos here and fifteen אמות
Amos here and then you have this opening, right, which actually had
a curtain in front of it. So how big was the opening?
Do the math. Twenty, right? Fifteen, fifteen, twenty. Okay. So the opening
of the חצר Chatzer is twenty אמות. Amos. So why don't we
say it's twenty אמה Amah width rather than ten אמה Amah width?
Because that's called a פתח. Petach. Okay. So let's
take a look. So מה להלן, Mah lehalan,
the same way over there חמש ברוחב עשרים, Chamesh berochav esrim, it
was five high and twenty and
twenty wide. אף כאן חמש ברוחב עשרים. Af kan chamesh berochav esrim.
So
here too why don't we allow an opening that's five high and
twenty wide? It's just a little funny why it's mentioning how high
it is, but the basic point is why the same way the
opening of the חצר Chatzer was twenty wide, let's allow the opening
here of the מבוי Mavoi to be twenty wide. And so the
גמרא Gemara says, no. פתח שער החצר אקרי. Petach shaar hachatzer ikri.
The opening of the gate of the חצר Chatzer is what it's
called. פתח סתם לא אקרי. Petach stam lo ikri. Not just an
opening. This is what Michael said. Gates could be bigger than normal
openings. So maybe there it's considered the opening of the שער. Shaar.
I know, but conceptually it was. Right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, ואי בעית אימא, Ve-ee ba'it eima, so maybe that's why
the גמרא Gemara gives another reason. If you want to give another
answer, כי כתיב קלעים חמש עשרה אמה Ki chtiv kla'im chamesh esreh
amah לכתף, la-katef, why does it say the קלעים kla'im are fifteen
אמות? amot? בגובה הוא דכתיב. Be-govah hu di-chtiv. This is a very
strange read of the פסוק. pasuk. It's saying that when this says
it's fifteen on each side, it does not mean fifteen wide. It
means that these קלעים kla'im are fifteen high. Okay, but we don't
know how wide they are. So maybe the actual opening is much
less. It says it's fifteen on each side. You assume it means
fifteen going in, right, closing off the third side. But they say
no, it just means that they're fifteen high. You don't know how
big the opening is so we can't learn from that. Very strange
read of the פסוק pasuk here. Okay, so they strictly analyze here,
it's fifteen higher than the... we'll get to that in a minute,
okay? So it says... yeah, but they say it means height. Okay.
גובה? Govah? So the גמרא Gemara says בגובה הוא דכתיב. be-govah hu
di-chtiv. גובה? Govah? What do you mean height is fifteen? והכתיב קומה
חמש אמות. Ve-hachtiv komah chamesh amot. It says height is five אמות
amot high. No, ההוא משפת מזבח ולמעלה. Hahu mi-sefat mizbe'ach u-lemala. That's
not five אמות amot from the floor, that's five אמות amot from
the top of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And as Harry pointed out, the
מזבח mizbe'ach itself does not sound like it's ten אמות amot in
the תורה, Torah, but okay, but according to one opinion, it reads
it as ten, so yeah, here's the picture here, right? So if
the מזבח mizbe'ach is ten אמות, amot, it's five אמות amot higher
than the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So that is a very, a very strange
re-read of the פסוקים, pesukim, which is that the height of the
curtains are not five אמות, amot, they're fifteen אמות. amot. When it
says fifteen on each side, it's not referring to how much it
goes in, it's talking about how high it is, and we don't
know how big the opening of the חצר chatzer is. All right,
anyway, what have we said with all of this? We have said
that the רבנן Rabbanan learn it out from the doorway of the
היכל, Heichal, which is called a פתח petakh because you learn the
משכן Mishkan from the היכל, Heichal, and that's what they learn the
maximum size that could be considered to be an opening. And רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda learns from an אולם, Ulam, or he learns from
somewhere else. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, והתנן, Ve-hatnan,
what do you mean? I'm sorry, רבי יהודה מפתחא דאולם גמר. Rabbi
Yehuda mi-pitkha de-Ulam gamar. Does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really learn from
the doorway of the אולם Ulam which is forty by twenty? והתנן,
Ve-hatnan, our משנה Mishnah says, ורחב מעשר אמה ימעט. Ve-rachav mi-eser amah
yema'et. If it's wider than ten, you have to make it smaller,
right? That's the end of our משנה. Mishnah. ולא פליגי רבי יהודה.
Ve-lo palgi Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not disagree. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only disagrees on the height, not on the width.
And by the way, in the first משנה Mishnah in סוכה, Sukkah,
there's a similar debate, that the first... that it says that a
סוכה sukkah that's higher than twenty אמות amot is no good, and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it doesn't matter how high it is,
but there there's no issue about how wide. So it seems like
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda only issue, the only disagreement is about height.
He doesn't disagree about width. But if he's really learning it out
from the אולם, Ulam, then he should disagree about width as well.
So the גמרא Gemara says, I really don't have much of a
voice today... I know. So it says, ואטו... Ve-atu... where am I...
ולא פליגי רבי יהודה. ve-lo palgi Rabbi Yehuda. So if רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is really learning it out from the אולם, Ulam, he
should argue about the width as well, but it's not present in
the משנה. Mishnah. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, פליגי בברייתא. palgi be-braita. He
does argue in the ברייתא. braita. דתניא, De-tanya, we saw in a
ברייתא, braita, ורחב מעשר אמה ימעט, ve-rachav mi-eser amah yema'et, more than
ten אמות amot you have to make it smaller. רבי יהודה אומר
אינו צריך למעט. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino tzarich le-ma'et. He doesn't have
to. So it's good. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda argues both on the
height and the width. He learns from a different doorway. וליפלוג במתניתין.
Ve-liplog be-matnitin. So why not argue in the משנה Mishnah if he
really argues? Funny question, right? Sometimes the גמרא, Gemara, you know, okay
fine, it's in a ברייתא, braita, but here the גמרא's Gemara more
skeptical as to whether he really is arguing. Why didn't he say
it in the משנה? Mishnah? פליגי בגובה והוא הדין לרוחב. Palgi be-govah
ve-hu ha-din le-rochav. You can figure it out. If he argues on
the height, presumably he argues on the width as well. ואכתי רבי
יהודה מפתחא דאולם גמר? Ve-achti Rabbi Yehuda mi-pitkha de-Ulam gamar? I'll still
challenge you, you say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda learns out from the
doorway of the אולם. Ulam. והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we saw in the ברייתא,
braita, מבוי שהוא גבוה מעשרים אמה ימעט. Mavoi she-hu gavoha mi-esrim amah
yema'et. If the crossbeam is higher than twenty אמות amot high, you
have to lower it. רבי יהודה מכשיר Rabbi Yehuda machshir עד ארבעים
וחמשים אמה. ad arbaim ve-chamishim amah. Like before, your fifty אמות amot
high could still be good. ותני בר קפרא, Ve-tani Bar Kappara, and
בר קפרא Bar Kappara says, עד מאה אמה. ad me'ah amah. It
could be a hundred אמות amot high. So what's the problem? What
did we say before the parameters of the אולם's Ulam the door
of the אולם Ulam was? You remember how high we said it
was? Forty by twenty. So if he is learning from the אולם,
Ulam, then how could he say forty or fifty? How could he
say a hundred? Forty should be the maximum limit. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, בשלמא לבר קפרא... Bi-shlama le-Bar Kappara... now interestingly,
although בר קפרא Bar Kappara says a hundred, we actually can make
it work for בר קפרא. Bar Kappara. For בר קפרא Bar Kappara
we can make it work. גוזמא. Guzma. A hundred is an exaggeration.
Okay, nobody really thinks a hundred means a hundred. So fine, a
hundred means forty. That's fine. אלא לרבי יהודה מאי גוזמא? Ela le-Rabbi
Yehuda mai guzma? But according to the version that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says forty or fifty, there's no exaggeration. He says forty or
fifty. Fifty is not based on the אולם. Ulam. He should have
just said forty. Right, so that's true, but תוספות Tosafot discusses that.
But anyway, okay. אלא... Ela... נ' מנא ליה? nun minaley? What does
he know, fifty? אמר רב חסדא המתניתא אתיא סייעתא לרב. Amar Rav
Chisda hamatnisa atya siyata le-Rav. So now the גמרא Gemara actually steps
back from its entire discussion. Until now we've been assuming it's all
learned out from either the היכל Heichal or the עולא, Ulla, because
the היכל Heichal is perfect. It's exactly the dimensions that are in
the משנה, Mishna, 20 high and 10 wide. And once we said
that the חכמים Chachamim hold by the opening of the עולא Ulla
of the היכל, Heichal, we said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda holds by
the opening of the אולם. Ulam. So now the גמרא Gemara is
saying, you know what? It has nothing to do with the אולם
Ulam and the היכל. Heichal. We're distracted by that, that's really not
what it's based on, because if it was based on, you don't
understand רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda's position. So let's take a look. He
says, המתניתא אתיא סייעתא לרב. hamatnisa atya siyata le-Rav. The ברייתא braita
just sort of made רב Rav make a mistake and think that
it was really based on the parameters of the אולם Ulam or
the היכל. Heichal. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, מבוי
שהוא גבוה מכ' אמה ימעט מפתחו של היכל. Mabui she-hu gavo'ah mi-chof
amma yema'et mipitcho shel Heichal. So if it's higher than 20 high,
higher than the opening of the היכל, Heichal, you should make it
lower. So a ברייתא braita directly connected it to the היכל.
Heichal. הוא סבר, Hu savar, he thought, assumed, מדרבנן מפתחו
של היכל גמרי, רב יהודה מפתחו של אולם גמר. midrabbanan mipitcho shel
Heichal gamri, Rav Yehuda mipitcho shel Ulam gamar. If the rabbis are
learning it from the opening of the היכל, Heichal, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda is learning it from the opening of the אולם. Ulam. ולא
היא, Velo hi, it's not true. רב יהודה מפתחא דמלכי גמר. Rav
Yehuda mipitcha demalchei gamar. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda doesn't base himself on
any opening of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or any doorway in
any פסוקים. pesukim. He just bases himself on like real-world experience, you
know, doorways of kings, of palaces. I mean out there, yeah, there
are doorways that are very high, there are doorways that are very
wide. There's no reason to limit it to 20 high or to
10 wide. So he's not learning it from an alternative model the
same way the חכמים Chachamim are. So he's not denying that the
חכמים Chachamim are learning it from the opening of the היכל. Heichal.
That's too attractive of a parallel to a מבוי, mabui, 20 by
10, which is exactly the parameters of the משנה. Mishna. But רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda is not learning it from a different opening. רב
יהודה's Rav Yehuda's just saying in general openings don't have any fixed,
you know, height or width or so on, and therefore you don't
have to limit it. So he's in the maximum lenient position because
then it could have been stricter. Right. Your standard house doors is
less than that.
That's true, that's true. Okay. So now we have a more latitude
in terms of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda not to
assume that he's learning it from the אולם. Ulam. ורבנן, Verabbanan, and
the rabbis now, the
גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אי
מפתחו של היכל גמירי, Ei mipitcho shel Heichal gemiri, if they're really
learning it from the doorway, now that we've said that רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda might not be learning it from the doorway of the
אולם, Ulam, now we're a little bit skeptical whether the rabbis are
learning it from the doorway of the היכל. Heichal. Maybe also the
rabbis just sort of sat down and figured out what's a reasonable
parameters of a door. Because if they really are learning it from
the doorways of the היכל, Heichal, so גמירי ליעבד ליה דלתות כהיכל,
gemiri li'ebad ley daltos ke-Heichal, then why not say it needs doors?
The היכל Heichal had doors, right? So why just say, oh, as
long as you have not more than the height and the width?
But maybe to be called a doorway you need doors, that's the
היכל Heichal had doors. אלמה תנן, Alama tnan, why do we teach
in a משנה, Mishna, הכשר מבוי, hechsher mabui, what do you need
for make a מבוי mabui kosher? בית שמאי אומרים לחי וקורה, Beis
Shammai omrim lechi vekora, you need both a vertical and a horizontal
beam, ובית הלל אומרים לחי או קורה, u-Beis Hillel omrim lechi o
kora, either vertical or horizontal beam. So you certainly don't need a
whole doorframe and you certainly don't need doors. So how could you
really say you're learning it from the היכל? Heichal? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, היכל לצניעותא בעלמא הוא דעבידי. Heichal litzniusa be'alma hu
de'avidi. The היכל, Heichal, it would have been called a doorway without
the doors. The doors were to provide privacy but not to make
it considered a doorway. Now I don't know who ever told the
גמרא Gemara that, right? It doesn't really answer the question. We see
that they had doors. Why don't you say every doorway needs doors?
And the answer is, nah, we assume that that would have been
considered a doorway without the doors. The doors were to create privacy.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, let's try the other way. אלא
מעתה לא תהני ליה צורת הפתח, Ella me'atta lo tehani ley tzuras
hapesach, why does a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach allow it to be
more than 10 אמות amos wide? Remember we taught that in the
משנה, Mishna, if it's more than 10 אמות amos wide, you make
a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. But I don't get it, the גמרא
Gemara says, the opening of the
היכל, Heichal, the door of
the היכל Heichal was 10 אמות amos wide with a צורת הפתח,
tzuras hapesach, right? Because it was a doorway, it had a צורת
הפתח. tzuras hapesach. So maybe even with a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach
it can't be more than 10 אמות amos wide. דהיכל נמי צורת
הפתח הוה ליה, De-Heichal nami tzuras hapesach hava ley, it had a
צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach, it was a real doorway. ואפילו הכי י'
אמות הוא דהוה, ve-afilu hachi yod ammos hu de-hava, it was only
10 אמות amos wide. אלמה תנן, Alama tnan, why do we teach
in our משנה, Mishna, אם יש לו צורת הפתח אף על פי
שרחב מי' אמות אינו צריך למעט? im yesh lo tzuras hapesach af
al pi she-rachav mi-yod ammos eno tzarich lema'et? If it has a
doorway, even if it's wider than 10 you don't have to make
it less. Okay, so if you're really learning it out from the
היכל, Heichal, then you should be able, then either you should have
a greater requirement of doors, or if not that, you should certainly
say that a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach doesn't help you get more
than 10 אמות amos wide. So the גמרא Gemara says מידי הוא
טעמא אלא לרב? miydi hu ta'ama ella le-Rav? We're only talking according
to רב. Rav. רב Rav was the one that compared it to
the היכל. Heichal. So by the way, this is important because here
this line, we're only talking according to רב, Rav, signals that you
can understand the rabbis' position of 20 by 10 not at all
related to the היכל. Heichal. We've already said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
isn't
based on the אולם, Ulam, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
just bases himself on his own understanding of what a doorway is,
but at least the rabbis are based on the היכל. Heichal. Now
the גמרא Gemara is saying even the assumption that the rabbis look
at the היכל Heichal is all just according to רב. Rav. Another
opinion would be the rabbis and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda are just
like any other... Another opinion would be and the Rabbis and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda are just like any other שיעורים shiurim are just
disagreeing on parameters and it's not based on specifically the היכל Heichal
or the אולם. Ulam. But anyway, but this is according to רב
Rav that says we are basing ourselves on the היכל. Heichal. מתני
ליה רב יהודה לחייא בר רב קמיה דרב. Matni leh Rav Yehuda
le-Chiya bar Rav kamay de-Rav. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda bar taught this
משנה Mishna to חייא Chiya the son of רב Rav in the
presence of רב Rav and here's how he taught this משנה: Mishna:
אינו צריך למעט. Eino tzarich lema'et. He says if you have a
צורת הפתח, tzurais hapesach, you do not have to make the doorway
smaller than
ten אמות. amos. אמר
ליה Amar leh and רב Rav said to him, אף מאי צריך
למעט. Af mi'ei tzarich lema'et. No, that's the wrong version of the
משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna should read that even if you have
a צורת הפתח, tzurais hapesach, it has to be less than ten
אמות. amos. So, I'm sorry, I'm really losing my voice. So what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is the following, just to refresh us
where we are, which is you have this courtyard, walls on three
sides, certainly not a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it might even be
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Rabbinically you need something on the fourth
wall. You need a לחי lechi or a קורה. korah. Conceptually what
that's doing is it's defining it as a doorway and if it's
defined, this opening as a doorway, then it's not considered an opening,
it's considered part of the structure, a doorway, and it's like it's
a fourth wall. That satisfies a rabbinic demand. Okay, what are the
maximum parameters that you could still legitimately call this a doorway? So
the משנה Mishna said it can't be higher than twenty אמות amos
high and ten אמות amos wide. If however you actually have a
צורת הפתח, tzurais hapesach, an actual structure that looks like a real
door frame, then it could be even wider than ten אמות. amos.
That was the משנה. Mishna. The גמרא Gemara says where do you
get these parameters twenty and ten and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda disagreed,
so רב's Rav focus was learning either from the opening of the
אולם Ulam or the
opening of the היכל Heichal
which was twenty by ten.
By the end the גמרא Gemara says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
maybe is not basing himself on any בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash structure,
just סתם stam saying that the parameters are different and maybe even
the חכמים Chachamim are saying are not basing themselves, but according to
רב Rav the חכמים Chachamim are basing themselves on the היכל. Heichal.
And the last question we have is then how could you take
more than ten אמות amos and say you solve it by צורת
הפתח tzurais hapesach if the היכל Heichal had a צורת הפתח tzurais
hapesach and was limited to ten אמות amos wide? And the answer
in the end is you're right, according to רב Rav who says
it's based on the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the היכל's Heichal
opening, even with a צורת הפתח tzurais hapesach you'd be limited to
ten אמות amos because that is the reality in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. That's extremely important for us for making עירובים. Eiruvs. Can
we have a צורת הפתח tzurais hapesach that's on a space bigger
than ten אמות? amos? All of our צורת הפתח tzurais hapesachs are
on bigger than ten אמות, amos, right? I mean you think about
how far distance they are from one another,
the posts and the wire and so on. Anyway, according to רב
Rav it would not work on more than ten אמות, amos, but
according to not רב, Rav, then yeah. So we'll see more about
that tomorrow.